A Finding Aid to the Charles Henry Hart Autograph Collection, 1731-1918, in the Archives of American Art aaa.hartchar
Archives of American Art
Charles Henry Hart autograph collection
1731-1918
aaa.hartchar
Archives of American Art
226 Items
The Charles Henry Hart autograph collection dates from 1731-1917 and consists of 226 letters, portrait prints, and other documents signed by American artists.
Hart, Charles Henry
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Scope and Contents note
The Charles Henry Hart autograph collection dates from 1731-1917 and consists of 226 letters, portrait prints, and other documents signed by American artists.
Originally titled by Hart as "The History of Art in America as Told in a Remarkable Collection of Autograph Letters and Documents of Celebrated American Artists of the Eighteenth, Nineteenth, and Twentieth Century," the collection includes letters and other items signed by Thomas Anshutz, John J. Audubon, William Merritt Chase, Frederic Edwin Church, John Singleton Copley, Kenyon Cox, Thomas Eakins, Jervis McEntee, Samuel F.B. Morse, Charles Willson Peale, Raphaelle Peale, Rembrandt Peale, Rubens Peale, Titian Peale, James Daivd Smillie, Gilbert Stuart, Thomas Sully, Abbott Handerson Thayer, John Vanderlyn, Elihu Vedder, John Quincy Adams Ward, Benjamin West, James Abbott McNeill Whistler, and many others.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Charles Henry Hart autograph collection, 1731-1917 (226 items; Box 1-5)
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Henry Hart (1847-1918) was a historian, lawyer, writer, and director, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1882-1904. Widely, he published on the subject of 18th and 19th century portraiture in the United States.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection is available on microfilm reel D5, available at Archives of American Art offices and for interlibrary loan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Charles Henry Hart autograph collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 1954 as an anonymous gift. It is assumed that Hart assembled the letters. Original collation was two letterbooks entitled "The History of Art in America as Tolk in a Remarkable Collection of Autograph Letters and Documents of Celebrated American Artists of the Eighteenth, Nineteenth, and Twentieth Century."
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds the personal papers of Charles Henry Hart, dating from 1774-1930, bulk 1888-1918.
Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Chase, William Merritt, 1846-1916; Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919; Eakins, Thomas, 1844-1916; McEntee, Jervis, 1828-1891; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827; Peale, Raphaelle, 1774-1825; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Peale, Rubens, 1784-1865; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885; Smillie, James David, 1833-1909; Stuart, Gilbert, 1755-1828; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872; Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921; Thomas Anshutz; Vanderlyn, John, 1775-1852; Vedder, Elihu, 1836-1923; Ward, John Quincy Adams, 1830-1910; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903; Artists--United States--Autographs; Artists--United States--Portraits; Autographs -- Collectors and collecting ##lcsh; Autographs--Collections
- Charles Henry Hart autograph collection, 1731-1918; Series 1; 226 Items Box 1-5
  Arrangement note
  The documents are arranged in rough alphabetical order and reflect Charles Henry Hart's original order.
  Scope and Contents note
  "The History of Art in America as Told in a Remarkable Collection of Autograph Letters and Documents of Celebrated American Artists of the Eighteenth, Nineteenth, and Twentieth Century" is a collection of signatures of 18th, 19th, and 20th Century American artists on letters, receipts, an indenture, and exhibition announcements. Also found are twenty-six prints, most of which are portraits of artists.
  - Ans-Bri, 1841-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Anshutz, Thomas
    Audubon, John J.
    Ball, Thomas
    Bierstadt, Albert
    Blashfield, Edwin Howland
    Bristol, John Bunyan
  - Bro-Cla, 1754-1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Brown, Henry Kirke
    Brown, George Loring
    Browere, John Henri Issac
    Brown, Mather
    Carpenter, Francis Bicknell
    Chapman, John Gadsby
    Chase, William Merritt
    Christy, Howard Chandler
    Church, Frederic Edwin
    Claypoole, James
  - Cof-Dan, 1775-1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Coffin, William Anderson
    Cole, Thomas
    Cooke, George
    Copley, John Singleton
    Cox, Kenyon
    Cranch, Christopher Pierce
    Crawford, Thomas G.
    Crospey, Jasper Francis
    Cummings, Thomas Seir
    Curran, Charles Courtney
    Danforth, Moseley Isaac
  - Dar-Eak, 1817-1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Darley, Felix Octavius Carr
    Dewing, Thomas Wilmer
    Dickinson, Anson
    Dougherty, Thomas
    Dunlap, John
    Durand, Asher Brown
    Eakins, Thomas
  - Eas-Gra, 1807-1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Eastman, S.
    Eicholtz, Jacob
    Edmunds, Francis William
    Elliott, Charles Loring
    Falconer, John M.
    Ferris, J.L.G.
    Fisher, Alvan
    Flagg, George Whiting
    Flagg, Jared Bradley
    Fraser, Charles
    Fuller, George
    Fulton, Robert
    Furness, William Henry Jr.
    Gerry, Samuel Lancaster
    Gifford, Sanford Robinson
    Glass, James W.
    Grafly, Charles Allen
    Gray, Henry Peters
    Grayson, Clifford Prevost
  - Gre-Hun, 1828-1892 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Greenough, Horatio
    Greenough, Richard Saltonstall
    Grimes, John
    Harding, Chester
    Hart, Joel T.
    Harrison, Thomas Alexander
    Hart, James McDougal
    Hovenden, Thomas
    Hubbard, Richard William
    Hunt, W.
    Huntington, Daniel P.
  - Ing-Lin, 1793-1897 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Ingram, Charles Cromwell
    Inness, George
    Joett, Matthew Harris
    Jocelyn, Nathaniel
    Jones, Hugh Bolton
    Kensett, John Frederick
    Kost, Frederick W.
    Krimmel, John Lewis
    Lambdin, George Cochran
    Lathrop, Francis Augustus
    Lawson, Thomas Bayley
    Le Clear, Thomas
    Leslie, Charles Robert
    Leslie, Robert
    Linen, George
    Linford, Charles
  - Low-Mig, 1810-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Low, Will Hicok
    MacMonnies, Frederick William
    Maverick, Peter Rushton
    Mayer, Frederick Blackwell
    Maynard, George Willoughby
    McEntee, Jervis
    Mead, Larkin Goldsmith
    Mignot, Louis Remy
  - Mil-Mur, 1818-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Miles, Edward
    Millet, Francis Davis
    Mills, Clark
    Moeller, Louis
    Moran, Benjamin
    Moran, Thomas
    Morse, Samuel F.B.
    Martin, Homer Dodge
    Morton, John Ludlow
    Murphy, John Francis
  - Nas-Rob, 1792-1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Nast, Thomas
    Neagle, John
    Page, William
    Palmer, Erastus Dow
    Palmer, William Launt
    Peale, Charles Willson
    Peale, Raphaelle
    Peale, Rembrandt
    Peale, Rubens
    Peale, Titian
    Pennell, Joseph
    Perry, Roland Hinton
    Ramage, John
    Read, Thomas Buchanan
    Richards, William Trost
    Richards, Thomas Addison
    Robertson, Alexander
  - Rot-Smil, 1743-1911 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Rothermel, Peter Frederick
    Rossiter, Thomas Pritchard
    Sargent, Henry
    Sargent, John Singer
    Saint-Gaudens, Augustus
    Sartain, John
    Shaw, Joshua
    Shirlaw, Walter
    Smedley, Will Thomas
    Smibert, John
    Smillie, James David
  - Smit-Tar, 1715-1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Smith, Francis Hopkinson
    Smith, J.R.
    Staigg, Richard Morrell
    Story, George Henry
    Story, William Wetmore
    Stuart, Gilbert
    Sully, Thomas
    Sully, Lawrence
    Suydam, James Augustus
    Tarbell, Edmund Charles
  - Tha-Twa, 1807-1892 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Thayer, Abbott Handerson
    Tisdale, Elkanch
    Tompkins, Frank Hector
    Trumbull, John
    Tryon, Dwight William
    Tuckerman, Henry T.
    Twachtman, John Henry
  - Uhl-Wat, 1806-1892 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Uhle, Albrecht Bernard
    Valentine, Edward Virginius
    Vanderlyn, John
    Vedder, Elihu
    Volk, Leonard, W.
    Waldo, Samuel Lovett
    Ward, John Quincy Adams
    Warner, Olin Levi
    Watrous, Henry Willson
  - Wei-Wya, 1800-1901 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Weir, Julian Alden
    Weir, John Ferguson
    Wertmuller, Adolph Ulrich
    West, William Edward
    West, Benjamin
    Whistler, James Abbott McNeill
    Wilson, Alexander
    Wilson, Matthew
    Wyant, Alexander
  - Robertson, 1801 (Box 4)
    Robertson, Archibald
  - Warne, 1731 (Box 5)
    Warne, Stephen